This honestly might have been the biggest bag fumble that I have seen in recent AI history.
Anthropic just put the banhammer down on anybody that is using Anthropic's subscription
to power their open claw. Rob Zalkos found this initially. Major cloud code policy clear
from Anthropic using OAuth tokens obtained through cloud free pro max accounts in any
other product tool or service, including the agent SDK, we'll come back to that, is not permitted.
We kind of knew this was coming. We definitely knew it was against their terms of service to
use your Anthropic subscription outside of their core products, meaning Cloud Desktop,
Cloud Cowork, Cloud Code, but we all wanted to use it in OpenClaw. And the craziest part,
it doesn't mention OpenClaw once, but it definitely looks like they directed this at OpenClaw.
Here's their specific policy language from their documentation. The OAuth authentication is
intended exclusively for Cloud Code and Cloud AI. Using OAuth tokens obtained through Cloud,
free, pro, or max accounts in any other product, tool, or service, including the agent SDK,
is not permitted and constitutes a violation of the consumer terms of service. And people got
pissed, including myself. This is just such a bad look for them. Let me take a step back and
explain how this all happened. First, what is OpenClaw? If you haven't been on X in the last
three weeks, then the quick summary of OpenClaw is it is an incredibly personal and capable AI
assistant that can be run locally and can be powered by any of the Frontier models. Initially,
OpenClaw was called Clawdbot, C-L-A-W-D, not Clawd as in Anthropics Clawd. Then about three weeks ago,
OpenClaw absolutely exploded in popularity. Then a few days after that, Peter Steinberger,
the creator of OpenClaw, was contacted by Anthropic and was told, you got to change the
name. It is too close to our trademarked Claude, C-L-A-U-D-E. And of course, he probably knew that
was coming once it exploded in popularity. And so he had to change the name. There was a brief
moment in time where it was called Maltbot, but eventually it was renamed to OpenClaw. And the
OpenClaw moniker is very interesting I going to tell you why in a little bit And by the way if you want to get ahead my team created a free ebook all about open claw use cases specifically how to implement them
how to get them going, why they're valuable, and so much more. Go download the ebook. It's
completely free. I'll drop a link in the description below. So why does the OAuth token actually
matter? Why is everybody talking about this? Well, first, it was the default way to get open claw
set up and there's a reason for that anthropic tokens are incredibly expensive if you go through
the api which is still allowed and they give a significant discount on a per token basis to the
subscription so if you're using cloud code or cloud co-work or just the cloud interface directly
the price per token that you're paying is significantly less than if you go to the api
directly. So of course, people wanted to use their subscription. And by the way, this is not some way
to get freebie tokens. You are still paying Anthropic for your subscription. Previously,
I was paying $20 a month. As soon as I started using OpenClaw, I upgraded to their max plan,
which is $100 a month. Shortly after that, I wanted more tokens. And so I was paying $200
a month for their increased max plan. I mean, look at some of these prices. This is API model
pricing. Here's Claude Opus 4.6, $25 per million output tokens. Claude Sonnet 4.6, a little less
expensive, but still $15 per million output tokens, $5 per million input tokens, and $3 per
million output tokens, respectively, for Opus 4.6 and Sonnet 4.6. Now, those numbers don't sound
like a lot of money, but it adds up very quickly. I was burning through my quota through the
subscription. And briefly after Anthropic shut off access through the OAuth system, I switched to the
API and I'm going to show you how very expensive it was. And so this is what the subscription panel
looked like. You got a five hour rolling quota and it would fill up and then you would have to
wait or you could buy extra usage down here. Then you also had your weekly limit. And for the $200
a month plan, I was able to use a good amount of my Claude subscription without really worrying.
Okay, now let me show you how expensive the API directly is going to be for OpenClaw usage.
So here's Claude Opus 4.6. And as you can see, each request just basically saying hello to your
OpenClaw bot uses about 50 tokens for me which is crazy And that just a simple hello Imagine if you actually doing any kind of coding or modification or analysis content ingestion
none of that matters. It is all 50,000 tokens as a minimum baseline. So with some quick calculation,
we can see 50,000 token input. That is again, the bare minimum with zero output is 25 cents.
every time I say hello to Opus 4.6, it is 25 cents. And it's not that much cheaper for Sonnet 4.6.
This is not sustainable in the least. So of course, I switched it. And keep in mind,
it is significantly higher for context above 200k. And that can happen all the time. If it reads the
code base, it happens. If it's loading a bunch of content into the context, that happens. So
it's just so expensive. Okay, so now back to this original tweet, and there was a lot of confusion,
specifically because of this line right here, including the agent SDK. The agent SDK is an
endpoint that allows you to build agentic loops using Anthropic. And a lot of people thought,
hey, that's kind of weird. I'm using your own product. Why are you preventing me from using
my Anthropic subscription with it? Then Tariq from Anthropic clarified, kind of still a little bit
confusing apologies this was a docs cleanup we rolled out that's actually caused some confusion
nothing is changing about how you can use the agent sdk and max subscriptions so there you go
you can still use it with the agent sdk but even more clarification we want to encourage local
development and experimentation with the agent sdk and claude-p if you're building a business on top
of the agent sdk you should use an api key instead we'll make sure that's cleaner in our docs and
And this really angered a lot of people, as I mentioned.
This is a tinkerer's community.
It is a builder's community.
A bunch of people started paying Anthropic
and then paying Anthropic more
because they were using OpenClaw.
It's a fun side project.
This is not a business.
This is a personal project, at least for me.
And if it's not a personal project, I would understand that.
Now I get it.
If you go through the Anthropic subscription,
you're paying about 90% less
than if you were going to the API directly.
So Anthropic is like, we're losing money.
We only want that to be available in our own products.
But it still hurt and it left a sour taste in my mouth.
So of course I switched off of Anthropic.
All right, so let's look at the timeline of events now,
because this is really a telling story and why it put even more of a sour taste in the community mouth So first Claudebot goes viral And then a few days after that Anthropic forces Peter to change the name from Claudebot
then Motebot, then OpenClaw, finally OpenClaw. Then Peter flew to San Francisco, met with the
leading AI labs, including OpenAI. And then about a week and a half later, OpenAI acquires Peter.
Then yesterday, just a few days after that, Anthropic blocks OpenClaw OAuth usage.
And then just that same day, OpenAI says, go for it.
Use our OAuth through Codex.
In fact, it was Peter who said that they allow it.
So Andrew Warner says, breaking Cloud OAuth officially not allowed.
We knew that.
Then this would be a great time for Sam Altman to step in and let us use OpenAI subscription
with OpenClaw.
and Peter replies, that already works. OpenAI publicly said that. Incredible. This is really
one of the greatest bag fumbles and bag pickups of all time. Okay, so all that aside, what am I
actually doing with OpenClaw? Which models am I using? Before I had a very simple setup, I was
using Opus 4.6 for almost everything. I would offload some of the coding to my Cursor CLI agent,
but mostly I was using Opus 4.6 because it just has the best personality. So now my entire system
is much more complex. I don't love it, but I just didn't want to continue throwing so much money at
Anthropic and it was just so expensive to use the API. So here is what I do now. Yes, I am using my
ChatGPT subscription, which they allow for OpenClaw. Now for coding, my security council,
my platform council, my business meta-analysis, my innovation council, those all go to GPT 5.3
Codex X High Fast. And that is offloaded to my cursor agent CLI. The CRM standard goes to GPT
5.2. A bunch of things that should just be really fast and easy like notification classifiers,
re-rankers, those all go to GPT 5 Mini and the knowledge-based summarizer, prompt sync review,
and the default overall model goes to GPT 5.2.
So yes, I am primarily using ChatGPT now.
I have Sonnet 4.6 and Opus 4.6 Thinking as backups.
I'm also using Gemini.
Gemini 3.1 just dropped,
so I'm definitely gonna be testing that,
but I just didn't love what happened here.
Let me know what you think.
If you enjoyed this video,
please consider giving a like and subscribe,
and I'll see you in the next one.